She rocks. She rules. She reigns.
The Princess Diaries is a comedy, family, romance
film directed by Garry Marshall.
A socially awkward but very bright 15-year-old girl being raised by a single mom discovers that she is the princess of a small European
country because of the recent death of her long-absent father, who, unknown to her, was the crown prince of Genovia.
She must make a choice between continuing the life of a San
Francisco teen or stepping up to the throne.
Mia Thermopolis, played by Anne Hathaway.
Queen Clarisse Renaldi, played by Julie Andrews.
Lilly Moscovitz, played by Heather Matarazzo.
Helen Thermopolis, played by Caroline Goodall.
Joe, played by Héctor Elizondo.
Michael Moscovitz, played by Robert Schwartzman.
The Princess Diaries is a 2001 American coming-of-age comedy film produced by Walt
Disney Pictures, directed by Garry Marshall, and written by Gina Wendkos.
Based on Meg Cabot's 2000 young adult novel of the same name, it stars Anne Hathaway (in her film debut) and Julie Andrews, with a
supporting cast consisting of Héctor Elizondo, Heather Matarazzo, Mandy Moore, Caroline Goodall, and Robert Schwartzman.
The plot follows Mia Thermopolis (Hathaway), a shy American teenager who
learns she is heir to the throne of a European kingdom.
Under the tutelage of her estranged grandmother (Andrews), the kingdom's queen
dowager, Mia must choose whether to claim or renounce her title.
Feeling confident about the novel's film potential, Cabot's agent pursued producer Debra Martin Chase about adapting
The Princess Diaries into a feature-length film, which she pitched to Disney upon reading the book.
After obtaining the film rights, Disney originally greenlit the project under the title The Princess of Tribeca, reverting it once its
setting was changed from New York to San Francisco, where the majority of the film was shot between September and December 2000.
Marshall agreed to direct because he found the story ideal family entertainment.
Despite having little involvement in the film's production, Cabot was
consulted about various changes to its story and characters.
Hathaway won the lead role over several established young actresses in her motion picture debut, while the film marked the
end of Andrews's semi-retirement from acting and return to Disney films, her first since Mary Poppins (1964).
The Princess Diaries premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Los Angeles on July 29,
2001, and was theatrically released in the United States on August 3.
A sleeper hit, the film grossed $165.3 million worldwide, defying industry expectations as
journalists had expected the film to underperform due to its G rating and subject matter.
It received mixed reviews for its plot and themes,
though Hathaway's performance was praised.
The film's success is credited with establishing Hathaway as a
bankable actress and reviving Andrews's film career.
A sequel, The Princess Diaries 2: Royal Engagement, was released in
2004, and a third installment is in development.
The film explores themes of princess, high school, based on novel or book,
grandparent grandchild relationship, heir to the throne.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.